Ashley Montagu Papers
Ashley Montagu Papers
1929-1987
Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999
19 linear ft.
Papers of the American anthropologist. Collection contains book manuscripts (1943-1967); published and printed material (1929-1967), including articles by and about Montagu; book reviews.
149318
Biographical History
Ashley Montagu (1905-1999) was a British anthropologist and social biologist, perhaps best known for his critical analysis of the question of race.
Montague Francis Ashley Montagu was born Israel Ehrenberg in London, England on June 28, 1905. He studied at the University of London (1922-1925) and the University of Florence (1928-1929). He came to the United States in 1930, received his Ph.D. in 1937 from Columbia, and was naturalized in 1940.
Montagu's first professional position was as a Research Associate at the British Museum of Natural History (1926-1927). Over his career he was Assistant Professor of Anatomy at New York University (1931-1938), Associate Professor of Anatomy at the Hahnemann Medical College and Hospital (1939-1949), Chairman of the Department of Anthropology at Rutgers University (1949-1955), Regents Professor at the University of California, Santa Barbara (1962); and lecturer at Princeton University (1978-1983). Montagu and his wife, Marjorie Helen Peakes, had three children.
Montagu was deeply interested in applying the findings of the social and biological sciences to the improvement of the human condition; Marcus Goldstein of Tel Aviv University remembered him for his "fearless and blunt attack on works and issues that he felt were scientifically wrong, and perhaps more important, were or could be socially harmful." (quoted in Steven Harnad's article "Ashley Montagu: Anthropologist And Social Biologist"). He wrote more than 50 books and many more articles related to the field of anthropology and social biology. Among his best-known books are Coming Into Being Among the Australian Aborigines (1937), Man's Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race (1942), The Natural Superiority of Women (1953), The Elephant Man (1971), Race and IQ (1975), The Nature of Human Aggression (1976), and The Dehumanization of Man (1983). He was the producer, author and director of the film "One World or None" (1946).
The deepest defeat suffered by human beings is constituted by the difference between what one was capable of becoming and what one has in fact become. -- Ashley Montagu
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ashley Montagu Papers include correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence consists of two incoming letters.
Subject files consists of one photograph of Ashley Montagu signed by the photographer, Editta Sherman, and assorted other photographs, including one of Montagu with Albert Einstein.
Manuscripts includes those of books by Montagu ( Human Heredity; The Biosocial Nature of Man; Anthropology: An Introduction to the Study of Man), and essays (Mothering; What is a Child; and The Role of the Social Sciences), books edited by Montagu ( The Concept of Race; Culture and the Evolution of Man: and Genetic Mechanisms in Human Disease), a discussion series with Virgilia Peterson on "The Nature of Human Nature," and manuscripts of others (Isadore Rubin, Sexual Life After Sixty).
Published material includes bulletins, journals, a news release, magazine articles, pamphlets, programs and reprints containing articles, speeches or book reviews by Montagu or material about him or his activities.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender. Montagu's manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type and within that alphabetically by title. Manuscripts of others are arranged alphabetically by author and one unsigned manuscript appears at the end of the series. Published material is subdivided alphabetically by type; within that, magazine articles are arranged chronologically while reprints are arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science and medicine; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.; Anthropologists -- United States.; Anthropology.; British Americans.; Physical anthropology.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Anthropologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Photographs, except for Sherman one, gift of American Philosophical Society, 2010.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1953; 1963 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Photographs (Oversize 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - The American way of Life
      - Corrected typescript, undated (Box 2)
      - Galley proofs, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Galley proofs pp. 81-85, undated (Box 3)
    - Anthropology: An Introduction to the Study of Man
      - Corrected typescripts, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Carbon copy with corrections pp. 1-28, undated (Box 3)
      - List of illustrations, undated; corrected copy (Xerox) (Box 3)
      - Corrected copy, pp. 1-19, undated; xerox (Box 3)
    - The Biosocial Nature of Man
      - Corrected typescript, undated (Box 3)
      - Carbon copy, p. 24-98, undated (Box 3)
    - The Cultured Man
      - Page proofs pp. 1-287, undated (Box 3)
      - Page proofs pp. 1-288, undated (Box 4)
    - Design for Happiness
      - Typescript copy pp. 1-120, undated (Box 4)
      - Carbon copy pp. 1-125, undated (Box 4)
    - The Direction of Human Development
      - Page proofs pp. 1-204, undated (Box 4)
      - Page proofs pp. 205-404, undated (Box 5)
      - Page proofs pp. 1-402, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Genetic Mechanisms in Human Disease
      - Page proofs pp. 1-231, undated (Box 5)
      - Page proofs pp. 232-462, undated (Box 6)
      - Fragments, undated (Box 6)
    - Human Heredity, revised paperback edition
      - Work sheets pp. 15-255, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Work sheets pp. 256-349, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Captions for figures 1-11, undated; corrected typescript (Box 7)
      - Index, undated; corrected typescript (Box 7)
      - Galley proofs pp 1-196, undated (Box 7)
      - Galley proofs pp. 197-432, undated (Box 8)
    - The Human Revolution
      - Work sheets, undated (Box 8)
      - Corrected typescript pp. 1-83, undated (Box 8)
      - Corrected carbon copy, undated (Box 9)
      - Xerox copy pp. 1-158, undated (Box 9)
      - Illustrations (figures 1-31), 1965; corrected xerox copy (Box 9)
      - Fragments, undated; printed copies with corrections (Box 9)
      - Queries to author, undated (Box 9)
      - Master proof, April 22, 1965 (Box 9)
      - Master proof, May 29, 1965 (Box 10)
      - Printed copy, marked, undated (Box 10)
      - Printed copies, undated (Box 10)
      - Xerox copy (complete), undated (Box 10)
      - Comments by unidentified critic, Jan. 21, 1964 (Box 10)
    - The Humanization of Man
      - Corrected typescript and work sheets pp. 1-121, undated (Box 10)
      - Corrected typescript and work sheets pp. 122-290, undated (Box 11)
      - Printer's proof, April 10-11, 1962 (Box 11)
      - Printer's proof, May 14-16, 1962 (Box 11)
      - Galley proof, undated (Box 11)
    - The Idea of Race
      - Work sheets pp. 1-281, undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Galley proofs, author's set, pp. 1-71, 1965 (Box 12)
    - An Introduction to Physical Anthropology (co-author C.L. Brace)
      - Page proofs for second edition pp. 1-252 (Box 12)
      - Page proofs for second edition pp. 253-524, undated (Box 13)
      - Page proofs for second edition pp. 1-560, undated; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Fragments with corrections, undated (Box 13)
      - Fragments with corrections, undated (Box 14)
    - Life Before Birth
      - Corrected typescript pp. 1-301, undated; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Complete carbon copy with corrections, undated (Box 14)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 14)
      - Galley proofs, undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Man and His Works, undated; corrected typescript pp. 1-101 (Box 15)
    - Man in Process
      - Galley proofs, author's set, undated (Box 15)
      - Page proofs with corrections, undated (Box 15)
    - Man's Evolution: An Introduction to Physical Anthropology (co-author C.L. Brace)
      - Corrected carbon pp. 1-273, undated (Box 16)
      - Galley proofs pp. 1-81, undated (Box 16)
      - Page proofs pp. 1-343, undated (Box 16)
    - Man's Most Dangerous Myth: The Fallacy of Race (4th edition)
      - Corrected page proofs pp. 1-163, undated (Box 16)
      - Corrected page proofs pp. 164-353, undated (Box 17)
    - The Myth of Race, undated; carbon copy (Box 17)
    - On Being Human
      - Duplicate proof with corrections, Feb. 17, 1950 (Box 17)
      - Galley proofs for new edition, 1966 (Box 17)
    - Physical Anthropology
      - Galley proofs: pp. 69-227, undated (Box 17)
      - With corrections, undated (Box 18)
      - Fragments, undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Prenatal Influences
      - Corrected printed copy pp. 1-128, undated (Box 18)
      - Work sheets pp. 129-538, undated; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Galley proofs pp. 179-206, undated (Box 19)
      - Galley proofs with corrections, undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - The Prevalence of Nonsense (co-author Edward Darling)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 21)
      - Page proofs with corrections, undated (Box 21)
      - Printer's proofs, with corrections, undated; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Books edited by Ashley Montagu
    - The Concept of Race
      - Work sheets pp. 1-81, undated (Box 21)
      - Work sheets pp. 82-209 and captions, undated (Box 22)
      - Work sheets pp. 9-123, undated (Box 22)
      - Galley proofs pp. 1-263, undated; 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Culture and the Evolution of Man, undated; galley proofs; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Genetic Mechanisms in Human Disease, undated; galley proofs (Box 23)
    - The Human Dialogue (co-editor Floyd W. Matson)
      - Galley proofs, undated; 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Galley proofs, undated; 1 set is marked up; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Discussion series
    - "The Nature of Human Nature" with Virgilia Peterson, undated; typescript copies of discussions 2, 4, 6, 7, 9, 10 (Box 25)
  - Essays
    - Mothering, Jan. 28, 1963; holograph (Box 26)
    - Mothering, Class and the Adult Personality, undated; holograph (Box 26)
    - Reflection on Violence in America, Nov. 26, 1963; holograph (Box 26)
    - The Role of the Social Sciences, Feb. 1, 1964; holograph (Box 26)
    - The Social and the Cultural, Feb. 9, 1943; holograph (Box 26)
    - The Socio-Biology of Love and the Process of Socialization, undated; holograph (Box 26)
    - What is a Child, 1963; holograph May 31, (Box 26)
    - Untitled, Oct. 30, 1966; holograph (Box 26)
    - Untitled, Feb. 16, 1967; holograph (Box 26)
  - Unidentified
    - Book
      - Work sheets (Box 26)
      - Corrected typescript, undated (Box 26)
      - Xerox copy of page proofs pp. 20-198, undated (Box 26)
      - Page proofs pp. 1-347 (with corrections), undated (Box 27)
      - Galley proofs, undated (Box 27)
      - Fragments and notes, 1945-1962; undated; holograph and typescript (Box 27)
  - Manuscripts of others
    - Berndt, Ronald and Catherine H. "Sexual Behavior in Western Arnhem Land" parts 1 and 2, 1948; 2 folders (Box 28)
    - Birket-Smith, Kaj "The Paths of Culture", undated; galley proofs, complete set (Box 28)
    - Greenblatt, Dr. Robert B., M.D. "The Hirsute Female", undated; galley proofs (Box 29)
    - Pounds, Dr. Norman J.G. "Global Geography and Man's Great Problems", undated; incomplete tentative manuscript (printed copy) for review (Box 29)
    - Rubin, Isadore "Sexual Life After Sixty", undated; galley proofs (Box 29)
    - International Graphics Society "Life and Its Marvels: Plant, Animal, Human", undated; dummy copy (not bound and with corrections) (Box 29)
- Published material
  - Bulletins
    - Academy of Medicine of New Jersey, Vol. 10, No. 2 June 1964 (2 copies), contains a speech by Ashley Montagu (Box 30)
  - Journals, contain articles by Montagu
    - American Journal of Physical Anthropology, Vol. XVIII, No. 2, Oct. - Dec. 1933 (Box 30)
    - ISIS, Vo. 37, Nos. 107 and 108, May 1947 (Box 30)
    - Journal of Existential Psychiatry, Vol. I, No. 4, Winter-Spring, 1961 (Box 30)
  - News releases
    - UNESCO Report on Race by Ashley Montagu, July 18, 1950 (Box 30)
  - Magazines
    - Articles about Ashley Montagu, 1956-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Articles by Ashley Montagu, 1956 (Box 30)
    - Article fragments, 1956 (Box 30)
  - Pamphlets by Ashley Montagu
    - Ernst Cassirer (Box 30)
    - Race and Other Kindred Delusions (Box 30)
  - Programs of symposia and conferences, Montagu was a member or participant
    - The Future of Man, 1959 (Box 30)
    - New England Conference on Human Nutrition, 1956 (Box 30)
    - The Next Hundred Years, 1957 (Box 30)
  - Reprints
    - A, 1933-1960 (Box 31)
      The African Origins of the American Negro and His Ethnic Composition (3 copies) Jan. 1944
      Aging of the Skull Jan.- March 1938
      Alěs Hrdlička, 1869-1943 Jan.- March 1944
      Anthropological Significance of the Musculus Pyramidalis and Its Variability in Man Oct. - Dec. 1939
      The Anthropological Significance of the Pterion in the Primates Oct. - Dec. 1933
      Anthropology and Genetics (3 copies) May 1945
      Anthropology and World History 1949
      Anthropology in Medicine 1947
      Anthropology: Physical Methods 1950
      Art, Curriculum, and Culture April 1954
      Artificial Thickening of Bone and the Piltdown Skull July 1960
    - B-D, 1929-1966 (Box 31)
      The Barcombe Mills Cranial Remains 1951
      Behavior As Viewed in the Behavioral Sciences and by American Education May 1959
      Biological Basis of Cooperation 1955
      Bronislaw Malinowski (1884-1942) 3 copies 1942
      The Buttocks and Natural Selection Oct. 1966
      A Case of Familial Inheritance of Oblique Inguinal Hernia Oct. 1942
      A Case of Pseudo-Alveolar Ultraprognatism Aug. 1932
      Cassirer on Mythological Thinking 1949
      The Chatelperron Skull 1952
      Climate and Reproduction 1939
      The Concept of Race in the Human Species in the Light of Genetics 1941
      A Consideration of the Concept of Race 1950
      Constitutional and Prenatal Factors in Infant and Child Health 1950
      Contributions of Anthropology to Psychosomatic Medicine June 1956
      Cultural Determinance of Sexual Status (2 copies)
      The Dentition of Identical Twins with Particular Reference to an Identical Pathological Condition, Dec. 1933
      Description of Three Instruments for Use in Orthodontic and Cephalometric Investigations, With Some Remarks on Map Construction Dec. 1931
      The Determination of the Naso-frontal Suture and the Nasion in the Living April 1937
      The Discovery of a new Anthropoid Ape in South America (2 copies) Sept. 1929
      Dislocation of the Femur Upon the Acetabular Notch in a Pre-Roman Briton (2 copies) Jan. 1931
    - E-H, 1938-1961 (Box 31)
      The Earliest Account of the Association of Human Artifacts with Fossil Mammals in North America (2 copies) Apr. 1942
      The Earliest Account of the Association of Human Artifacts with Fossil Mammals in N. America May 1944
      Four on War April 1943
      Le Fragment Cranien De Bury St. Edmunds 1949
      The Future of the Australian Aborigines 1938
      Human Nature and Religion 1961
      The Human Organism 1949
      The Human Organism and Reproduction, Heredity, and Growth (2 copies) 1952
      Human Values and Family Policy 1948
    - I-N, 1931-1959 (Box 31)
      Ignorance of Physiological Maternity in Australia 1941
      Ignorance of Physiological Paternity in Secular Knowledge and Orthodox Belief Among the Australian Aborigines 1940
      Infertility of the Unmarried in Primitive Societies 1937
      Infibulation and Defibulation in the Old and New Worlds 1945
      Intelligence of Northern Negroes and Southern Whites in the First World War 1945
      Karl Pearson and the Historical Method in Ethnology 1943
      Knowledge of the Ancients Regarding the Ape 1941
      The Location of the Nasion in the Living 1935
      Man - and Human Nature 1955
      The Medio-Frontal Suture and the Problem of Metopism in the Primates 1937
      Mr. Simple on Racial Equality 1945
      The Myth of Blood 1943
      The Natural History of the Human Teeth, by John Hunter: A Study 1935
      Natural Selection and the Mental Capacities of Mankind (2 copies) 1947
      Natural Selection and the Origin and Evolution of Weeping in Man 1959
      The Nature of Race Relations (2 copies) 1947
      Neoteny and the Evolution of the Human Mind undated
      Nescience, Science and Psycho-Analysis (3 copies)
      Nota su un tipo raro di pterion nel Gorilla 1931
      A Note on an Anomalous Iliac Muscular Bundle Associated with an Anomalous Femoral Nerve 1943
    - O-R, 1931-1954 (Box 32)
      On a Post-Frontal and Orbital Elements in a Young Gorilla Skull 1931
      On the Origin of the Domestication of the Dog 1942
      On the Phrase "Ethnic Group" in Anthropology (3 copies) 1945
      On the Relation Between Body Size, Waking Activity, and the Origin of Social Life in the Primates 1944
      The Origin and Nature of Social Life and the Biological Basis of Cooperation (2 copies) 1948
      The Origin of Subincision in Australia (2 copies) 1938
      Origins of the American Negro (3 copies) 1944
      Ph.D. Thesis Regulations 1939
      The Physical Characters of African and Other Non-American Negroids (3 copies) 1945
      Physiology and the Origins of the Menstrual Prohibitions 1940
      Physiological Paternity in Australia 1937
      The Piltdown Mandible and Cranium 1951
      The Piltdown Nasal Turbinate and Bone Implement: Some Questions (2 copies) 1954
      The Premaxilla in Man 1936
      Race, Caste and Scientific Method (3 copies) 1941
      Racial Intelligence (2 copies) Jan. 1948
      Racism, The Bomb and the World's People (2 copies) 1946
      Racism, Religion and Anthropology 1947
      A Rare Case of Osteomalacia With Severe Caries of the Maxillary Canine Teeth in a Captive Baboon 1935
      A Reconsideration of the Galley Hill Skeleton 1949 Reproduction, Heredity, and Growth 1949
    - S-Y, 1939-1955 (Box 32)
      Scientific Invention and Social Consciousness 1939
      Seventeenth Century Account of Burial Customs Among the Indians of South Carolina 1940
      Sex Order of Birth and Personality 1948
      The Significance of the Premaxillary Diestema in Pithecanthropus Robustus 1944
      The Significance of the Variability of the Upper Lateral Incisor Teeth in Man (2 copies) 1940
      The Skillful Skull 1943
      The Social Function of Science (2 copies) undated
      Social Instincts April 1950
      Sociometric Methods in Anthropology Feb. 1945
      Some Psychodynamic Factors in Race Prejudice 1949
      A Spurious Portrait of Robert Hooke (1653-1703) 1941
      Tennyson's Prediction of the Invention, Use and Misuse of the Aeroplane 1943
      Theognis, Darwin, and Social Selection 1947
      Time Binding and the Concept of Culture (3 copies) 1953
      A Unique Development of the Premaxilla in the Gorilla (2 copies) 1942
      United Nations Economic and Security Council, Statement by Experts on Problems of Race 1951
      Vesalius and the Galenists 1955
      A Yankee Doctor in England in 1859 (2 copies) 1943
    - Book reviews, 1938-1950; undated (Box 32)
      The Biology of the Negro by Julian Herman Lewis, 1942
      Blood Groups and Transfusion by Alexander S. Wiener, undated
      The Development of the Vertebrate Skull by G.R. deBeer, 1938
      El Egaño de las Razes by Fernando Ortiz, 1947
      Escape From Freedom by Erich Fromm, 1942
      Malaria in the Upper Mississippi Valley 1660-1900 by Erwin H. Ackerkneicht, 1946
      Man in the Primitive World: An Introduction to Anthropology by E. Adamson Hoebel, 1949
      The Nature-Future Controversy by Nicholas Pastore, 1950
      The Stone Age of Mount Carmel by McCown and Keith, 1940
      The Vertebrate Eye and Its Adaptive Radiation by Gordon Lynn Walls; The Retina by S.L. Polyak; and Vertebrate Photoreceptors by Samuel R. Detwiler (3 copies), 1943
    - Of others, 1948; 1955 (Box 32)
      Beutner, R., M.D. The Inhalation Anesthetics, review, undated
      La Barre, Weston The Social CeU, 1955
      Unidentified book review, 1948